know 90 percent of serotonin is produced
in
this the digestive tract
because the digestive system has a
direct interface with our environment
and so it's really important that we
start there uh given that 70 to 80
of our immune system is in the digestive
tract
and you know 90 of serotonin
is produced in this the digestive tract
um so you know wow
dr reynolds can you pause right there
and repeat what you said how much
a percentage of serotonin is produced in
the
in the colon you said
ninety percent what was the number nine
i still didn't know the number
ninety percent
and we have all these mental health
issues for low serotonin levels in our
brain causing depression
anxiety and a host of other mental
health issues
and it's all can be resolved in our
we can forget 90 wow percent of what we
need
in a from our colon wow that's powerful
i would love
documentation on that i also want to
mention this too
the since we're talking about serotonin
okay production serotonin dopamine all
of the neural peptides that
impact um uh mood and behavior
uh they require vitamins b6 and
magnesium and zinc for their synthesis
so if you are depleting on these basic
nutrients
you your body will not be able to
synthesize and produce
and even transport some of these
important
biomolecules so it's really important
again that's why
you know i part of the reason why i'm a
naturopath
to be honest with you because our part
of our curriculum is to delve deep into
biochemistry
and the relationship of how our
environment
influenced um you know the the
physiology of our body at a basic level
the cell
cellular level and um and understanding
the role of nutrition and how
nutrients impact physiology it's really
important especially if you're trying to
um you know
help with chronic disease and prevent
and increase
longevity so um yeah and and systems
biology approaches
i'm looking at the the digestive system
and how that impacts the nervous system
and how the digestive system impacts the
immune system
cardiovascular system
all of these systems got created to be
connected
not you know if you have a high you have
dyslipidemia
or high cholesterol you give them a
statin and just ignore
everything else that's going on with the
person you have to address what's
happening in other organ systems and
because they all work in concert with
one another
and so people are
in the area of many doctors now
know it's really important to address
what's happening in the digestive system
um i i can't stress that enough so yeah
so when i work with patients
i'm looking at their digestive health
and health and
one thing i i usually do for people i
have them do a comprehensive stool
analysis
because it allows me to give more
insight into what's
actually happening in their digestive
tract in terms of
what bacteria are there if you don't
have any parasites
or fungal fungus we do have fungus that
naturally inhabits the digestive tract
but it's when it over proliferates it
becomes a problem
and the over proliferation becomes an
issue when there's an
imbalance what we call dysbiosis uh
an imbalance in those organisms in the
digestive tract
we have commensal bacteria such as
lactobacilli
and bifidobacterium in these particular
species for example
um lactobacilli and we're going to talk
about how you can
you can improve your digestive health
utilizing the
most first-line intervention for
digestive health are the use of
probiotics but we're going to talk about
um how to use them
and who's a candidate for probiotics um
and so because there's some people who
should not be using probiotics
um and so in the context of the immune
system
lactobacilli plantarum species
of bacteria was shown in studies to
reduce the common code
bifido or lactobacilli rhamnosus
is actually shown to improve the gut
lining
and reduce inflammation and also
it's been shown to reduce hsv herpes
simplex virus clearance
this particular strain of bacteria so we
know
that you can even target the types of
bacteria
and utilize them as tools for for
targeting certain conditions
and there are certain strains of
bacteria like bifidobacterium
um used been shown to increase natural
killer cell activity
and elderly populations so if you're
one of those if you're you know all in
that population then you might be
a terrific candidate for a probiotic
or if you've had a long-standing history
of antibiotic use
you you will be a candidate of of a
probiotic
um i think doctors if you if they're
prescribing antibiotics they should
co-treat
with a probiotic because a lot of times
they kill off everything
and so we need to replenish the
digestive tract and restore the health
and balance to the
microflora